<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Datapunks</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2019-04-01T21:43:33-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Woodruff</name>
   <email>david@datapunks.ca</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Setup a intake and registration platform in 18 min with PowerApps</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/18/data-apps-fast/"/>
   <updated>2018-09-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/18/data-apps-fast</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Custom data platforms in PowerApps are fast to build. In this video, see just how quickly an intake and check-in system can be composed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z67Ufdew914&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What a Canadian data-nerd learned from 13 American inner-cities</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/04/what-i-learned-from-13-innercities/"/>
   <updated>2018-09-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/04/what-i-learned-from-13-innercities</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Data and social work. Admittedly, not the most iconic duo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet as Canadian governments dole out millions in grants for social service delivery, they want something back in return: service data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I administrate the database of an inner-city social work agency using a leading case management software solution. In school I fell in love with the potential power of user-friendly mobile experiences and I was greatly disappointed when I realized our database for entering service data was not mobile compatible, and actually recommended you use Internet Explorer. In 2018. I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article-pictures/20180904-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; color: #C0C0C0; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;@morebeerlesswork as seen on the streets of Oakland. Also my face when using ETO Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t exactly an online hub where people discuss what technology homeless-serving organizations use. There’s a small handful of organizations in any one city, but it’s unlikely such organizations have a person dedicated to data, if they even have a database at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting nearby non-profits in Alberta was beneficial, but I had a limited sense of 1) how a city’s most vulnerable receive services and 2) what organizations use to track data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to see in person the handful of strong organizations who work everyday with extreme poverty, and the tools they use to support their mission. So I set out on an adventure. 13 American inner-cities in 2 months. I chose the USA because Canada doesn’t have 13 major cities, and if it did, flying between them would cost a small fortune. Luckily, the non-profit I worked for supported my mission and let me gallivant for a couple months to record my findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-quick-note&quot;&gt;A quick note&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent seven days at most in a city. What I saw in that time cannot do complete justice to each’s unique social and political history. I don’t mean to paint a complete picture of any one city.
I felt Southern Hospitality in Nashville
I approached each city with what I phrased “guerrilla networking”. I would show up in a city and walk in, or send an email, to organizations I thought relevant or interesting. I’d attend any relevant event I could and try and find my way to an organization or idea.
My first success was with Room In The Inn in Nashville, a fantastic organization that answered my weekend email and arranged a tour the next week. Their kindness nearly melted my face.
The organization was rife with caring practices. Instead of a meal line to get food dished on disposable plates, they gave table service to their clients. “It takes a bit longer, but it’s worth it”, my guide remarked. Every week their staff wash the feet of their service participants, an outstanding humble act in any sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My pin collection at that point. Room In The Inn specifically made alternate pins of their slogan, “Love Your Neighbor Y’all”, for the Canadian players on their hockey team. So cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-saw-antipoverty-in-atlanta&quot;&gt;I saw Antipoverty in Atlanta&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlanta was the most aggressive against it’s inner-city population. I was shocked.
Most telling is the city’s long, nasty battle with Atlanta’s then largest homeless shelter: the Peachtree-Pine shelter. The city was suing the shelter for unpaid utilities, and actually shut off water at one point. This felt like some strange alternate time-line, I never thought a city could be so violent towards its homeless population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article-pictures/20180904-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; color: #C0C0C0; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;In Atlanta’s downtown core you can be fined for panhandling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the city administration’s attitude was disappointing, I found solace in the resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I volunteered a few hours for AHRC, a harm-reduction based organization that does needle exchange with in Atlanta’s rougher neighbourhoods. They could be in deep legal trouble if they couldn’t prove they provide needles for a “legitimate medical purpose”. I also served a meal with Food Not Bombs in the middle of the “Tourist Triangle” which feeds the homeless and makes Atlanta’s inequality visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before leaving Atlanta there was a massive fire that collapsed the I-85 interstate bridge. An individual was smoking crack underneath a bridge with flammable construction materials nearby. In my mind, it stands as a clear consequence of pushing people with addictions into the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-recognized-luddism-in-san-francisco&quot;&gt;I recognized Luddism in San Francisco&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally used as derogatory term for a technophobic older person, classic Luddites get a bad rap in modern discourse. The original Luddites were not against new technology and “progress”, they were weavers against their livelihoods being destroyed by unskilled factory jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visited San Francisco 2 years before this trip and was dazzled by the start-up scene because as I was building an app of my own. Everyone in San Francisco seemed to have a great idea, and the willingness to break the status quo enthralled me. I entered excited to see the intersection of innovative technology, a progressive mindset, and growing issues of inequality. I left with a heavy heart and a new view of Silicon Valley.
I went directly to the notoriously un-touristic Tenderloin. Upon visiting one particular grassroots organization, the program manager informed me that there were no plans in starting a case management database, and if you brought that idea to the directors you’d meet heavy resistance: Why fund the companies and attitudes that contribute to San Francisco’s rising inequality? I met with other organizations nearby supportive of data, but the grassroots organization always stuck with me. I’d never met an organization against a database. From what I saw, the new tech-bro overlords have done very little in relieving the inequality they shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sight of a sunny BMW dealership and office document startup on either side of a overpass became sour when I saw the small group of tents huddled underneath, a small barricade built around it as if fend off gentrification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-felt-true-community-in-austin&quot;&gt;I felt true community in Austin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked in Austin if a purpose of my trip was to find another city to live. I answered no, but the tiny house village on the outskirts of Austin I visited the next day made me feel I’d been living my whole life wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community First! Village by Mobile Loaves and Fishes entered my radar curiously: a new friend at a couchsurfing meetup recommended it to me. It follows the name exceptionally well. To be a member of the Community First! village you must prove your willingness to join a community that works, plays, and lives together in true village fashion, just as I envisioned humans did before the industrial revolution.
Somewhere between the forge, chicken coup, outdoor kitchen, and communal firepit, I realized I’d never felt such love and respect in a place, let alone a place brought together by poverty. “Magical” is a word that continually comes back to mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community First! has no service delivery database, but they didn’t need it. Anybody who walked the village could tell there was something special happening here. And when that ‘anybody’ has a few commas in their bank account, Community First! gets a couple more tiny homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community First! shook my worldview, and reminded me of the true goal: a place when anyone can be valued, loved, and respected. I hope to scale that sentiment to North America’s largest inner-cities.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
